嘿，大家好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么上一次我们讨论了投影矩阵，我们基本上，在前几期中
so last time we talked about projection matrixes, and we basically, over the last few episodes
我在我们的应用中有了一个在OpenGL中构建的数学库
I've gotten a math library into our application here, that we're building in OpenGL
所以今天我想说的是
so today what I want to talk about is
我猜在投影矩阵之后的下一步，那么我们有了投影矩阵
I guess the next step after the projection matrix, so we have projection matrixes
特别地，我们实现了一个比如正交投影的矩阵
and specifically we implemented like an orthographic projection
至于我们的视图，如果启动上次的程序，这样就能看到实际上有什么
for our view, if we just launch our program from last time, so that we can see what we actually had
我们设法把这个ChernoLogo绘制在了一个不同的位置
we managed to draw this ChernoLogo kind of in a different position
而不是在正确的纵横比的中心
not in the center of the correct aspect ratio
通过使用正交投影，就是我们这行代码提供的
by using an orthographic projection, which we provided over here in this line of code
所以那就是投影矩阵的一个阶段
so that's kind of one phase of it the projection matrix
但是这儿还有另外两个非常重要的矩阵
but there's also two other matrices that are very important
当我们在处理几何变换的时候
when we're dealing with the transformation of geometry
当我们在场景中渲染它时，那么首先是投影
when we render it in a scene, so the first being projection
然后我们还有一个叫做视图矩阵的东西，还有一个叫做模型矩阵的东西
but then we also have something called view matrix, and we have something called a model matrix as well
并且所有这些和每个顶点位置相乘
and that all of that gets multiplied together with our with each vertex position
计算出我们顶点在实际屏幕中的最终位置
to give us kind of the final position of the vertex in our actual screen
比如窗口内部，或者在电脑屏幕上的2D投影
like on inside our window, or in our kind of 2D projection that is on our computer screen
那么再说一次，这背后有很多理论，我以后可能会讲到
so again, lots of theory behind this, which I probably will cover at some point
但我今天想做的是，介绍这个概念，并向大家展示
but what I want to do today is, just kind of introduce the concept, and actually show you guys
如何访问它，它的用途是什么
how you can access it, and what it's used for
然后你们可以尝试一下，希望能通过这种方式学习
and then you can kind of play around with that, and hopefully learn it that way
因为那可能是一个更好的学习方法
because that's probably a better way of learning it
他们只是在学习很多理论，什么都不做，好了，那么直接切入正题吧
they're just studying a lot of theory, and not doing anything, okay, so let's get straight into it
模型视图投影mvp，或者我想，你们也可以把它反转为pvm
model view projection mvp, or in you know, if you reverse it pvm, I guess
但通常它被称为mvp，你们可能也听过那个术语mvp或mvp矩阵
but usually it's said as mvp, and you may have heard that term as well mvp or mvp matrix
所以那个代表模型视图投影矩阵
so that stands for model view projection matrix
并且那是一种经过每个顶点的变换管道
and that is kind of the transformation pipeline that goes through every vertex
现在我一直在说管道，但真的
now I keep saying pipeline, but really
我的意思是每一个mvp的字母都是一个单独的4x4矩阵
what I mean is that each one of those letters mvp is a separate 4 by 4 matrix
并且所有这些矩阵以模型视图投影那种顺序相乘
and that and all of those matrices get multiplied together in that order model view projection
现在在OpenGL中，当我们处理到列主排序时
now in OpenGL, since we deal with column major ordering
实际上，它们都是反过来的，就像我们要把它写出来一样
it's actually done in kind of reverse each, like if we were to write it out
在我们的着色器代码中或者在C++的glm代码中
in it inside our shader code or inside our glm code in C++ here
它可以是投影*视图*模型
it would be projection times view times model
而像Dirext3D和DirextX，因为它们确实处理的矩阵是行主序的
whereas like DirextX and Dirext3D, because they did deal with row major order for matrices
那实际上就是mvp，模型，视图，投影
that would actually be mvp, model view projection
实际上，你们会在这个等式的左边找到顶点的位置
and you'd actually have your vertex positions on the left side of that kind of equation
至少是在等式之外，但那是第一个东西
non less out of the equation, but that would be kind of the first thing
如果你们从左到右读取，相乘的时候，而OpenGL是相反的
you multiply if you read left to right, whereas an OpenGL is reverse
所以实际上这个mvp并不一定决定了顺序
so the fact that this mvp doesn't necessarily define the order
我们可以在这里讨论很多可能不需要提及的东西
lots of stuff we could talk about here that we probably don't need to mention
但是我们有这三个矩阵
but the idea is that we have these three matrices
它们定义了顶点位置的不同东西
and they kind of define different things for our vertex position
因为最后我们把所有的矩阵相乘
because what happens in the end is we multiplied all the matrices together
我们乘以那个矩阵，得到的矩阵和我们的顶点位置相乘
and we multiplied that matrix, that resulting matrix with our vertex position
那个顶点位置就是几何图形的顶点位置
and that vertex position is the vertex position of our geometry
存储在顶点缓冲区中，并且那些所有相乘
which is stored inside our vertex buffer, and that kind of all that multiplication
将顶点转换为它应该在计算机屏幕上实际屏幕上的位置
transforms that vertex into where it should be on our actual screen on our computer screen
那就是这一切的目的
that's what this is all for
那么我们有上次讲过的投影矩阵
so we have the projection matrix which we talked about last time
这是专门用来转换这种我们选择使用的空间的
which was specifically for actually converting this kind of whatever space we choose to work with
到标准化设备坐标
into normalized device coordinates
这意味着我们要从我们所处理的空间转换到
meaning we're converting from whatever space we're dealing with
不管是正交投影还是透视投影
and whether that be orthographic or perspective
转换到-1到1的映射，在每个xyz轴上
into a -1 to 1 mapping, in kind of every axis xyz
那就是投影矩阵的作用
that's what the projection matrixes is responsible for
如果你们还没有看的话，一定要看看那个视频
definitely check out that video if you haven't already
模型和视图矩阵有点不同
the model and the view matrix are something a little bit different
视图矩阵有时被称为视觉矩阵，是相机的视图
the view matrix sometimes called the eye matrix is kind of the view of the camera
所以这或多或少是一种模拟相机的方法
so it's a way for us to kind of simulate a camera more or less
模型矩阵是我们基本上用来模拟模型矩阵的一种方法
and then the model matrix is a way for us to basically simulate the model matrix
所以这个模型就是我们实际绘制的这个模型
so the model being the model that we're actually drawing
那么我们绘制的这个顶点，这个矩阵具体的说就是这个模型的一个变换
so the vertex that we're drawing, and the matrix specifically is just a transformation of the model
所以为了把它化成更简单的形式，先不考虑投影
so to put this into more simple terms, projection aside
因为那就定义了我们要处理的空间
because that just kind of defines like I guess what kind of space we deal with
视图矩阵是相机的位置，旋转，缩放等等
the view matrix is the position, the rotation, scale whatever of our camera
然后模型矩阵是位置，这是变换
and then the model matrix is the position, there's the transform
所以就是我们对象中绘制的实际模型的位置旋转缩放
so the position rotation scale of our actual model that we're drawing of our object
那么我们就有对象变换和相机变换
so we have the object transform, and we have the cameras transform
现在重要的是要明白，归根结底的说，这些只是数学数字
now it's important to understand that, at the end of the day, these are just mathematical numbers
实际上我已经给了你们这个图解
the fact that I've kind of given you this illustration
如果我们有一个相机，我们有这个变换矩阵的模型
if we have a camera, we have this model kind of transformation matrix
那都是一种幻觉，在某种意义上
that's all kind of an illusion, in the sense that
你们不需要，你们不需要相机，你们可以
you don't like, you don't have to have a camera, you could just, you
我不知道，你们可以一直把相机放在中间
I don't know just, you could just have your camera in the center at all times
只要有这样的模型矩阵，就可以了
and just have the kind of model matrix, and that will work as well
因为实际上这些只是数字，不管怎样，它们会相乘
because really these are just numbers, and they will get multiplied together, anyway
你们可以有另一个矩阵，就像你们的第二个相机矩阵之类的
you could have another matrix, that's like your secondary camera matrix or whatever
有很多方法可以做到这一点，因为这并不重要
there's so many ways you can do this, because it doesn't really matter
它们只是矩阵相乘
they're just your multiplying matrix things together
你们要明白，就是那么简单
you have to understand that, it's as simple as that
我们处理的惯例是我们有一个视图矩阵
so the convention that we kind of deal with is we have a view matrix
那是专门用来代表相机的，位置和方向
that is specifically supposed to represent our cameras, kind of position and orientation
然后我们有一个模型矩阵用来表示我们的对象变换
and then we have a model matrix which is supposed to represent our objects transform
对象就是我们当前绘制的东西
object being the thing that we're currently drawing
因为我们要做的就是相乘
because what will happen is we're going to multiply
投影矩阵乘上相机矩阵乘上模型矩阵乘上顶点位置
the projection matrix with the camera matrix with the model matrix with the vertex position
我们待会再看那个
and we'll take a look at that in a minute
但从概念上讲，我只是想让你们理解我在这里介绍的东西
but conceptually, I just want you to understand that what I'm introducing here
就是两个不同的矩阵，视图矩阵和模型矩阵
are two different matrices, the view matrix and the model matrix
视图矩阵应该代表相机的位置和方向
the view matrix is supposedly supposed to represent our camera position and orientation
模型矩阵是用来表示对象变换的
and the model matrix is supposed to represent our objects transform
意思是通过变换，至于变换
meaning by transforming, by transforming
我可能也会专门为此做一个视频
I probably will make a video specifically on this as well
教OpenGL很困难，对吧，我也会做一期关于那个的视频
teaching an OpenGL is hard man, okay, I'm gonna make a video on that as well
但变换的具体意思是位置，旋转，缩放或平移
but transform specifically means kind of position rotation scale or translation
我应该说这就是我一直在寻找的方式，这是漫长的一天，伙计
I should say that's the way I was looking for, it's been a long day man
变换，旋转，缩放，简称TRS
translation translation rotation scale, TRS
变换的意思我想是我们物体的位置
translation meaning the kind of the position I guess of our object
这个旋转是朝向的旋转
the rotation being the orientation is kind of rotated in
然后缩放就是它的大小
and then the scale being kind of how big or small it is
也不需要统一缩放，所以你们可以改变
doesn't have to be uniform scaling either, so you might be able to change
比如，如果它是一个立方体，你们可以把它做成一个矩形或类似的东西
like if it's a cube, you could make it a like a rectangle of prison or something like that
我们以后肯定也会讲到
and we'll definitely get into that in the future as well
但那就是我的想法，不管如何，这个就先说到这儿吧
but that is the idea, anyway, I'm gonna stop talking
因为我觉得我又要唠叨18个小时了
because I feel like I'm just gonna ramble on for another 18h
让我们进入正题吧，看看我们能用这个新知识做些什么
let's just get into this and see what we can do with this newfound knowledge
那么现在，我们有一些基本顶点的位置在这里
so at the moment, what we have is kind of our base vertex positions which are over here
我们创建了一个顶点，抱歉，是投影矩阵，这是一个正交矩阵
we've created a vertex, a sorry, projection matrix, that is an orthographic matrix
从0到960，从0到540
that is kind of from 0 to 960, and from 0 to 540
否则它就是一个像素空间的投影
so otherwise it's kind of a pixel space projection here
因为每个单元是1个像素，这是我们的顶点位置
because every unit is 1 pixel, here are our vertex positions
这些都在顶点缓冲区内，我们在这里做的
and those are just inside our vertex buffer, and what we're doing here
这个result是我在CPU端模拟的乘法
well this result was just kind of me simulating that multiplication on the cpu side
但如果你们看我们的着色器在做什么，它也在做这个
but if you look at what our shader is doing, it's also doing that
从这个意义上说，就是读取mvp，我们传入这里的模型投影矩阵
in the sense that is taking our mvp, model  projection matrix that we're passing in here
然后乘以位置
and multiplying it with position
现在我们来看看mvp到底是什么，你们可以看到
now if we take a look at what mvp actually is here, you can see that
我们实际上传递的是这个proj，对吧，我们传递的是那个proj矩阵
what we're actually passing here is just this proj, right, we're just passing in that proj matrix
实际上我们没有任何视图矩阵或模型矩阵
we're not actually we don't have any kind of view matrix or model matrix
但是我们现在要做的是我们要做矩阵的加法
but what we're going to do now is we're going to add of matrix
这将是相机的位置
and what this is going to be is the position of our camera
那么在这一点上，我们需要决定，我们要如何移动相机
so at this point we need to decide, well, how do we want to move our camera
也许我们想要平移相机，我们不需要考虑旋转，暂时让这个简单点
maybe we want to translate our camera, we won't worry about rotation, just to give this simple for now
让我们把相机移到左边100单位
let's maybe move our camera, I don't know, 100 units to the left
现在这里有个技巧，我们这儿要做的是尝试移动相机
now here's a trick, what we're doing here is we're trying to move our camera
那么让我们花一分钟，就一分钟
so let's kind of for a minute, for brief minute
因为我会有一个关于相机的独立的视频
because I will have a separate video on cameras
就一分钟，让我们想想相机是什么
for a brief minute, let's just think about what a camera is, well
好吧，其实相机是不存在的
okay, there's not actually like a camera doesn't actually actually exist
根本就没有相机这东西，所以我们要如何模拟相机呢
there's no such thing as a camera, so how would we simulate a camera
我们看一下，我们有一个物体，比如这里的这个手机，我们有一个相机
well let's just see, we have an object, like this phone over here, right, we have a camera here
所以如果我想把相机移到左边，从技术上讲，那么物体就会移到右边
so if I want to remove the camera to the left, then the object would move to the right, technically speaking
那么如果我能将相机向左移动，那么物体就会向右移动
so if I can move the camera to the left, then the object kind of moves to the right
那就是发生的事情，我可能看不到什么东西
that's what happens, I probably can't see much something
我可能应该画个图，但如果你们喜欢，那就是我想要表达的
I probably should have just drawn a diagram, but that's kind of what I'm getting at if you like
OpenGL中没有相机这个东西
there's no such thing as a camera in OpenGL
我们能做的就是移动几何体，我们能移动顶点
all we can really do really is just move geometry around, we can move vertices around
所以为了模拟相机向左移动，我们需要做的是将所有东西向右移动
so to simulate a camera moving left, what we really need to do is move everything to the right
所以它是一种逆向运算
so it's kind of the reverse operation here
那么我要做的是创建一个平移矩阵
so what I'm going to do here is create a translation matrix
因为我想把所有东西都向右移动100单位
except since I want to move everything to the right 100 units
我要在这里写的是一个vec3，我只是移动所有的东西
what I'm actually going to write here is a vec3, where I'm just moving everything
就是-100，那么向左
-100, so to the left
因为那有点像将相机向右移动
because that will kind of be like moving the camera to the right
我把其他的都填上0，我们看看还有什么
and I'll just fill in 0 for the other units here, and let's see what else is once
那么我想我们应该做的是创建一个视图矩阵本体
so I guess what we should really probably do here is actually just create an identity view matrix
也就是其中的一个，然后通过实现那个来平移这个矩阵
which would mean one of these, and then translate that matrix by just doing that
我相信这会改变它的，现在要付出很大的代价
and I believe that should change it, now it takes a cost which is great
所以我们实际上必须，我想我们能做的
so we'll actually have to, what we could do I guess
在这里构造一个矩阵本体，然后像那样把它赋值给view
is probably end up constructing a identi matrix here, and then assigning it to view like that
很好，所以那就是我们的视图矩阵
all right, cool, so that's kind of our view matrix
现在我们要做的是这个mvp，会创建一个glm::mat4 mvp
so now what we'll do is this mvp thing will actually create a flm mat4 mvp matrix
现在就是proj乘以view
which will be that proj time to the view now
那么让我们把它传给这里的mvp，然后按f5运行程序，很好
so let's pass that into mvp here, and hit f5 to run now program alright, cool
所以这儿的结果就是，这个ChernoLogo向左边移动了100个单位
and so the result here is that, this ChernoLogo has just moved 100 units to the left
因为我们做的是我们把相机向右移动
because what we've done is we've moved our camera to the right
并且如果我们把相机向右移动
and if we move our camera to the right
这意味着我们现在看到的所有东西都向左移动了
it means that everything else we're now seeing kind of move to the left
我已经通过逆向运算模拟过了
and I've simulated that by just doing the reverse operation here
因为我在这里输入了-100，这实际上是将目标向左移动
because I'm typing a -100 here, which essentially ends up moving the objective left
这又是一个向右移动相机的模拟
which again is a simulation of moving the camera to the right
所以那就是它的工作原理
so that's how that works
显然，如果你们在一个相机类中，会有这种逆向运算的
obviously if you're at a camera class, you'll kind of this kind of negation
你们会自动化所有这些，接口会帮你们处理这些
you'll automate all that, and the api will take care of that for you
所以你们不用担心那个，但数学上就是这样的
so you don't have to worry about that, but mathematically that's how it works
将相机向左移动实际上就是将所有矩阵向右移动
moving the camera to the left is actually just moving all the matrixes to the right
所以在同样的标准下，因为我们在这里做的
so with this same principle, because all we've really done here
我的意思是你们看不出区别，我把它叫做视图矩阵
I mean you can't tell the difference, I've called it view matrix
但你们无法分辨我们将相机向左移动
but you can't tell the difference between us moving the camera to the left
还是要求物体向右移动，都是同样的结果
or ask moving the object to the right, same thing
所以这纯粹是这是如何运作的一种形象化的方法
so it's again purely a kind of way to visualize how this actually works
但从数学上讲，它们都是一样的，都是数字
but mathematically, it's just it's all the same, it's just numbers
所以我们现在要做的是创建这个模型矩阵
so what we'll do now is we'll create this model matrix
我再把这个模型变换一下
and I'll again translate the model somewhere
所以当我向右移动的时候，我们最终向右平移了这个相机
so we ended up translating this well the camera right, when I'm moving to the right
那么这里我要做的是把模型往上移一点
so what I'll do here maybe is move the model up a bit
那么也许我们会看到，向右移动200，向上移动200，应该这样
so maybe we'll see, we'll move a 200 to the right, and 200 up, and so we should
但我们最终应该让ChernoLogo更靠近屏幕中心
but we should basically end up with our ChernoLogo being closer to the center of the screen
我们把这些矩阵相乘，所以就是proj*view*model
and we'll multiply all these matrices together, so proj times view times model
按f5，你们可以看到现在我们有了ChernoLogo被移动到了另一个位置
hit f5, and you can see now we have the ChernoLogo being moved another
你们知道的，向上200单位，向右200单位
you know, 200 units up, and 200 units to the right
好了，那就是我们最后得到的，酷
okay, and that's what we end up with, cool
所以这个得到的矩阵就是我们的mvp就是模型视图投影
so this resulting matrix here is what our mvp is model view projection
并且再说一次，乘法的顺序是相反的
and again, the multiplication is kind of an reverse order that's to do with
事实上，所有数字的内存布局，它们是主列排列的事实
the fact the memory layout of all the numbers, the fact that they're in colum major
你们可以把OpenGL中的矩阵乘法理解为从右到左
you can kind of think of reading matrix multiplication in OpenGL as right to left
我们把模型，视图和投影相乘，那就是最终结果
so we multiply model with view with projection, that's just how it ends up working out
由于我们内存分布的方式
because of the way that we've laid out our memory
因为它们是OpenGL在着色器和显卡中期望的方式
because of the way they're OpenGL actually expected in the shader in the GPU
还有glm对我们的处理方式
and also the way the glm handles are for us
因为那就是OpenGL的这种规范
because of that kind of specification by OpenGL
不管怎样，那就是你们在这里看到的，三个矩阵相乘
but anyway, that's what you see here, three matrices multiplied together
为我们实际的顶点创建变换
which create the transformation for our actual vertices
就是这样，很简单
that's it, very simple
相机乘以物体的变换乘以那个proj
camera multiplied with the transform of our object multiplied with that proj
把所有东西转换成标准设备坐标
which converts everything into normalized device coordinates
那就是所有你们需要知道的矩阵乘法
that is basically all the matrix multiplication you need to know
如果你们担心3D或2D世界中的对象位置
if you're worried about position objects in a 3D or 2D world
就是这样，这就是所有需要知道的，显然你们可以做的不仅仅是变换
that's it, that's all there is to know, obviously you can do more than just translation
我只是给你们展示了一个简单的例子，我下次想做的是
I kind of just showed you with simple example, now what I want to do next time
因为我们在这一期中已经接触了所有这些模型视图投影的东西
because we've kind of touched on all this kind of model view projection stuff in this episode
非常棒，下次我想开始介绍透视投影
which is awesome, next time I want to actually start introducing perspective projection
可能会涉及到3D的东西
and maybe get into some 3D stuff
因为它对我们来说非常重要
now because it's going to be really important for us to
需要某种方式来控制这些参数的生存周期
have some kind of way of controlling these parameters live
因为我不能一直关闭我的应用
because I can't keep closing my application
更改代码，重新编译，更新，那将是非常痛苦的
changing the code, recompiling it, and updating it, that's going to be really painful
这对我来说真的很难证明，任何类似的东西
and it's really hard for me to demonstrate, anything like that
我要做的可能是集成ImGui，这是一种UI框架
what I'm actually going to do is probably integrate ImGui which is a kind of a UI framework
很容易使用UI的图层
really easy to use UI kind of layer that we can use for
实际上，UI控件是我们应用的一部分，我们可以用它来修改变量
actually kind of having UI controls as part of our application which we can use to modify variables
当我们的应用程序像调试层一样运行时
while our application is running kind of like a debug layer
非常容易使用的UI，下次我们可能会集成它
really easy kind of ui to use, so we'll probably integrate that next time
但除此之外，我们还得继续，继续用数学这个库
but other than that, we're just going to progress, keep going with this kind of maths stuff
希望很快就能进入透视投影
and hopefully get into perspective projections soon
想想我们如何在屏幕上呈现真实世界的物体
and think about how we can render real world kind of objects on the screen
无论是3D还是2D
whether that be 3D or 2D
我们可能会在3D和2D之间来回切换，还没决定
we might go back and forth between 3D and 2D, haven't decided yet
但那就是这个的要点
but that is kind of the gist of this
告诉我，你们对模型投影的看法
let me know what you guys thought of this whole model projection thing
我最后可能会为每个概念做更详细的视频
I am going to probably end up making more detailed videos about each concept
但我想先做一个完整的视频来介绍这个主题
but I kind of like to make an overall video just covering just introducing the topic first
因为这可能是足够的信息
because this is probably enough information
对于你们很多人来说，实际上开始做这个，并尝试它
for a lot of you, to actually start doing this yourself, and play around with it
那可能是最好的学习方式
and that's going to be probably the best way to learn
不管怎样，我希望你们喜欢这个视频，如果喜欢的话，就为它点赞吧
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video, if you did, you can hit that like button
你们可以直接访问patreon.com/TheCherno来帮助支持本系列教程
you can go ahead and help support this series by going and patreon.com/TheCherno
非常感谢所有可爱的赞助人，是他们让这个系列教程成为可能
huge thank you as always to all the lovely patrons who make this series possible
如果没有你们就没有这个系列教程
it wouldn't be here without you
下次见，拜
I will see you guys next time, goodbye